翻译
山山 颜值担当CC
GUO Hopsen
翻译
Oliver Monica-卡
大家好 欢迎来到Grand Tour特别节目
Hello and welcome to a Grand Tour special,
校对
清野过客  Natas Monica-卡 RN
我们将从这辆车开始 大众甲壳虫
which begins with this: the Volkswagen Beetle.
时间轴
木楠楠  Monica-卡 RN
我们都不喜欢这辆车
It's a car we hate very much
只有纳粹和嬉皮才喜欢这车
because it appeals only to Nazis and hippies,
甲壳虫原型车由希特勒下令研发
而我们 明显两个都不占
and we are neither of those things.
但是 如果你卸下车身
However, if you remove the bodywork
套上个更有趣一点的
and replace it with something a bit more fun -
像这样的东西
something like this--
你就造了辆沙滩车
you end up with a beach buggy,
简直妙不可言
and that's brilliant.
我们都爱沙滩车
We love beach buggies.
然而 威尔曼先生却颇有微词
However, Mr. Wilman disagrees.
他说 这东西真有那么好的话
He says that if they'd been any good,
它们肯定会流行起来了
they would have caught on,
然而并没有流行过
and he points out that they didn't.
所以他想了个计划
So he hatched a plan. And it's this:
他让我们仨一人买一辆甲壳虫
he said all three of us must buy a Volkswagen Beetle,
把它改成沙滩车
turn it into a beach buggy,
然后去一个
and then report with it
荒芜 崎岖 偏远的地方碰头
to a wild, rugged and extremely remote place--
就是这里 纳米比亚的沙滩
here on the coast of Namibia.
这是我的杰作
This is what I've built.
这辆车和
It's as close as you can possibly get
1964年 布鲁斯 梅耶斯造的
to the original 1964 beach buggy
初代沙滩车非常像
built by Bruce Meyers.
各种零件都来自50年代甲壳虫
Underneath, it is a 1950s Beetle--
底盘 悬架
Beetle floorpan, Beetle suspension,
引擎 变速箱
Beetle engine, Beetle gearbox.
还有前灯
It's got Beetle lights on it.
我甚至还装了甲壳虫时速表
I've even got a Beetle speedometer
和甲壳虫轮毂罩
and Beetle hubcaps.
堪称完美
It's brilliant!
这和史蒂夫麦昆在
This is a beach buggy very like the one that Steve McQueen drove
偷天换日里开的那辆几乎一模一样
in the original Thomas Crown Affair.
而且它在电影里就够好的话
- And if it's good enough-- - (HORN TOOTS)
-噢天啊 -哈哈
- Oh, God. - Ha-ha!
我被强行拖入了70年代
I've been joined by the 1970s.
♫ T.REX: "20th Century Boy"♫
好极了
Yes.
詹姆斯造的是沙滩车的历史
James May has built what a beach buggy was,
而我这 则是它可能的未来
what I've built is what a beach buggy can be...
如果你有那么点想象力
...if you have a bit of imagination
和紫色金属亮片漆的话
and some purple metal-flake paint.
哈哈哈
Ha-ha-ha-ha!
♫ Twentieth century toy, I wanna be your boy... ♫
这里 我觉得就是冒险的起点了吧
There, I believe, is the start point of our adventure.
♫ I wanna be your boy... ♫
真是个好地方啊
What an extraordinary place.
很惊人 你看 那么多海豹
It's amazing, isn't it? I mean, more seals.
大卫 艾登堡唯一没告诉我们的就是
What David Attenborough never told us about those
大卫 艾登堡 自然环保学者
海豹闻起来有多糟糕
is how bad they smell.
可惜 在我们的自然课堂继续下去之前
Sadly, before our nature documentary could go any further,
理查德 哈蒙德在雾中出现
Richard Hammond emerged from the mist.
噢你看 那不是沙滩车吧
Ooh, hello. That's not a beach buggy.
-对吧 -我不会这么叫它
- Is it? - Well, I wouldn't call that...
-啊哈 -噢天啊
- Ah-ha! - Oh, geez.
女士们先生们 丁丁
Ladies and gentlemen, Dick-tari!
Dick-tari:谐音daktari 美国儿童电影
主演为非洲兽医 穿衣与此时的鼹鼠类似
请看
Behold!
你穿的啥
What are you wearing?
你穿的那是什么
这可是在非洲啊
Well, I'm in Africa!
你这裤子
- (JAMES LAUGHS) - These trousers,
买的时候店员是不是说
did they say in the shop,
这裤子是黄色的 您真要买吗
"I'm afraid they are yellow, sir"?
当你一走 他们就说 太好了
When you left, they went, "Yes!
那东西挂了20年终于卖掉了
20 years we've had those on the hanger!"
闭嘴
- - Shut up.
然后我们就得开着这车
And then we must move over to this.
-嗯哼 -我们被要求
- Yeah. - We were told
造一辆沙滩车
to build beach buggies.
-嗯哼 -沙滩车
- Yes. - Beach buggies.
-这不是沙滩车啊 -不是
It's not a beach buggy. It isn't.
这就是啊
It is a beach buggy.
这不是 它还有车顶呢！
It isn't a beach buggy. It's got a roof!
而且这里面根本就没甲壳虫元素啊
There's no Beetle in here at all.
不 里面有甲壳虫的引擎
Yes, there is. Beetle engine in there.
好吧 这个立体车架...
OK, this space-frame chassis...
-是啊 -也是从甲壳虫上来的？
- Yeah. - Is it from a Beetle?
不是 -这些巨大的悬架
- No. - These enormous suspension components -
甚至都不能好好的呆在车身里
that don't even fit under the bodywork.
-你在后面竟然放了两个悬挂 -双减震嘛
- You've got two lots of suspension at the back. - Twin shocks.
-双减震？ -我喜欢这种越野的气氛
- Twin shocks? - I like an off-road sort of vibe.
要想到终点 我们得开过一片海滩
To get here, we had to drive on a beach.
-嗯哼 -我们的车没问题
-Yeah. -Ours have made it.
我的车可不需要两个避震器
I didn't need two lots of rear suspension on mine.
你看吧 当时只告诉我们来非洲
Look, we were told to come to Africa.
我也是
Neither did I.
如果能具体点 来圣莫妮卡海滩 那...
If we'd been told to go to Santa Monica Beach, then this, with its...
...蠢得不可思议的骚气涂装...
...incredibly vivid paint...
那是我见过最有金属感的车身了
That's the most metal flake I've ever seen.
世界上有没有那么一个沙滩
Any beach in the world.
-等下 那是什么？ -那是引擎
- Hang on, what's that? - That's the engine.
- V8! -那是什么引擎？ -V8！
- What engine is it?
我把V8放进了沙滩车！
I've put a V8 in a beach buggy!
好吧 其实 你没放进去
Well, no, you haven't.
你这车也太紧凑了
You've parked your beach buggy quite close.
它都不在车里！
It's not in it!
-它不在里面 -不在
- It isn't in it. No.
你强塞进了一个V8
You've reversed into a V8,
但用力还不够猛
but not quite hard enough.
它只进去了三分之一
It's only gone in a third of the way.
你们知道要把V8引擎
Do you have any idea how difficult it is
塞进沙滩车里有多难吗
to fit a V8 to a beach buggy?
-根本就不合适啊 -明显不可能
- Well, it doesn't fit! - It's obviously impossible.
没错 是不可能
Exactly, it's impossible.
但这不是普通的v8
This is no ordinary V8.
它本来是
It started out in life
路虎的3.5升V8引擎
as a 3.5 litre V8 from a Range Rover,
不过我微调了 现在它能输出180马力
but I've modified it, so it produces 180 horsepower.
我能说一句吗 你们在怀疑
Can I just say, you were doubting
我的沙滩车的可靠性
the credibility of mine as a beach buggy.
是啊
Yeah.
沙滩车的定义
The defining characteristic of a beach buggy
是一个风冷 四缸甲壳虫引擎
is an air-cooled, flat-four Beetle engine.
不 那不是引擎 詹姆士
No, that's not an engine, James.
那只是个风扇
That's just a fan.
你有多少马力？
How many horsepower does yours have?
94!
所以我这辆车的马力是你的两倍
So I have twice as many horsepower.
-你要知道 -发动机并不在车里啊
- Shall I tell you something? - They're not in the car, though.
-他们在啊 他们离得很近 -是啊
- They are, they're near it. - Yes.
很有趣 不是吗  我是说 整个就是--
It's interesting, isn't it? I mean, that is an entire--
没啥意思
Nothing about that is interesting.
这就是一张空白画布
This is a blank canvas
你可以尽情挥洒个性
onto which you could paint your personality.
-没错 -但你的不是
- Yes. - Yours has got
V8就那么挂在屁股上
a prolapsed V8 hanging out of its backside
还有那糟糕的涂装
and terrible paint.
我的就很华丽
Mine is a rather magnificent
Daktari主题的越野风格
"Daktari"-themed off-roader. ？
那上面什么都没有啊！
That's got nothing on it!
-你能解释... -这有点太无聊了
- You can express... - It is a bit boring.
...你的全部个性和标准
...all your personality, and it's standard.
这不是...你什么意思 标准？
It's not... What do you mean, standard?
这是辆沙滩车
It's a beach buggy.
这很高雅啊
- It's tasteful.
什么？
What?
-噢 -蝙蝠电话
- Oh. - The bat sat-phone.
我们收到一条来自...
We've got a message from...
制作人先生的信息
Mr. Wilman.
继续说
Right, go on.
“既然你们都开上了沙滩车...”
"Since you're in beach buggies..."
好吧 我们俩确实是
Well, us two are.
“既然你们已经开上了沙滩车，
"Since you're in beach buggies,
"就应该开向沙滩”
you will now drive to the beach.
额
Uh...
额 你不觉得
Uh...do you think
他的常识离家出走了吗
he's taken leave of his senses?
他地理从来没好过吧
Well, he was never that good at geography, was he?
确实不好 你们现在要开到沙滩上
No, he wasn't. "You'll now drive to the beach."
等下 哦不 这后面还有
Hold on. Oh, no, there's more.
你们将要去到的沙滩
"The beach to which you will drive
位于鳄鱼出没的库内内河边
is located on the crocodile-infested Kunene River
纳米比亚的最北边 与安哥拉接壤
at the northernmost point of Namibia, where it meets Angola.
远在1600公里之外
It's 1,000 miles away."
- 有1600公里  - 1600公里
- 1,000 miles? - 1,000.
我们现在最需要的是一张地图
What we needed at this point was a map,
于是我们决定沿着海岸北上
so we decided to head north up the coast
找到一个最近的村庄
and find the nearest town.
开始吧
Let the journey begin!
开着这样的车会是怎样的旅行呢
And what a journey it would be in these cars,
这些车诞生在一个有趣的时刻
cars that were born in interesting times.
那是1964年
So, it's 1964,
"青少年"这个词正开始出现在
the word "teenager" has started to appear
世界各国的字典里
in the world's dictionaries,
人们开始欣赏新式音乐
people are listening to new types of music,
他们在接触着新鲜事物
they're smoking new types of stuff.
接着 在加州 沙滩车出现了
And then, in California, the beach buggy arrived!
这太完美了
It was perfect!
男孩女孩 沙滩烧烤
Girls and boys, beach barbecues...
首要的设计准则是前轮轮眉要平坦
The first design criteria was that the front fenders were flat,
所以你可以在上面喝啤酒
so you could stand a beer on it.
汽车就该这么设计!
That's how you design a car!
吉米亨德里克斯有一台沙滩车 尼克松总统没有
Jimi Hendrix had a beach buggy and President Nixon didn't.
吉米·亨德里克斯 美国著名吉他手 歌手 作曲人
这就说明了很多问题吧
Tells you all you need to know.
我真正喜欢沙滩的地方是
What I really like about the beach buggy is that it's a testament
这是对人类精神胜利能力的证明
to the ability of the human spirit to triumph.
因为有人会看着甲壳虫说
Because somebody looked at the Beetle and said,
哦 这是世界上最万恶独裁者的遗存
"Well, that's the legacy of the world's worst dictator.
让我们把它改成一部沙滩车吧
Let's turn it into a beach car."
在烟雾迷离中
After a lonely hour
孤单的北行一个小时之后
of driving north through the swirling mist,
我们依然没有找到一个村子
we still hadn't found a town,
但是我们找到了些别的
but we did find something else.
天啊
Jesus.
我来告诉你们
I'll tell you what,
它上沙滩的时候
he must have been going at a right old lick
直接就这么蹭过来了
when he hit the beach.
肯定的
He must have been.
嗯 海在那边
Right, the sea is there.
有将近两公里呢
That's half a mile away.
我也觉得
I'd say so.
他先冲上沙滩
So he got it up the beach,
然后类似做了一个手刹过弯
and then sort of did a handbrake turn.
开足动力 把它滑上来  你去哪儿拉手刹
-Power-slided it in. -How do you do a handbrake...
讲真啊 它到底怎么到这里的
How did it get here, seriously?
我想说 我的乳头激凸了
Can I just say... my nipples are erect.
哦 外套磨的  不是
- What, 'cause of this jacket? - No.
太冷了
- Oh. - It's cold.
确实太冷了啊 嗯 是挺冷的
- It is, isn't it? - It's cold.
这可不是一个明智的穿衣策略
That's an unwise wardrobe strategy.
是啊 但是你知道
Yeah, well, you know,
非洲 在沙滩上 我以为
Africa, on a beach, I thought...
我也这么想的  我被震惊了
- So did I. - I'm surprised.
沙滩上有海上的哈雾
The beach has got the sea haar on it -
还有薄雾 浓雾 寒冷
mist, fog, cold.
如果你看那边 嗯哼
- If you look over there... - Hm.
阳光 蓝天
...sunshine, blue sky.
我们为什么不往内陆走  找沿海公路
- Why don't we just go inland... - The coast road.
找一个能把我们带到城镇的沿海公路
Find the coast road which will take us to a town.
那边艳阳高照 是个更好的注意
And that'll be in the sun. That's a better idea.
在提出了计划之后
With a plan worked out,
是时候再次上路了
it was time to get moving again.
哦 天啊
Oh, dear.
你把电瓶也改装了么
Did you modify the battery as well?
哦
- (IGNITION FAILS) - Oh...
很明显电瓶没充上电 不会吧
- It's obviously not charging up. - No.
因为我没改电瓶
Because I didn't modify it.
好吧
Yeah.
我看看我的还好不好使
I'll just see if mine works.
好耶  我也试试我的吧
- Oh, yeah. - Let me just try mine.
没问题
- Yeah.
推推看  啥
- Push? - Hm?
你能帮我推一下么
- Can I have a push?
在节目组帮我重新上路后
After the film crew had got me going,
我用我强大的马力去追其他人
I used my massive horsepower to catch the others.
但是当我们又碰面的时候
But by the time we were back together again...
天已经黑了
it was going dark.
正如你回头看到的 太阳已经落山了
The sun, as you can see over my shoulder, has set,
我们还是没找到一条路
and we still haven't found a road.
而且还开始变得非常非常的冷
It's also going to be very, very, very cold.
开灯
Lights on.
我们一定要找到一条路啊
We have got to find this road.
在这种地方开夜车
This is not going to be too clever...
可不明智
in the dark.
我随意地把手电筒安装在
I've rather crudely rigged up my torch,
挡风玻璃的框架上
wedged in the windscreen rail,
希望你们能通过镜头看到我的遗言
in the hope that you can see my last pieces to camera.
哦 见鬼
Oh, bollocks!
终于
Finally, though
我们好像要转运了
it looked like our luck had changed.
哦 你好 你好
Ooh, hello! Hello!
那是什么
What's that?
-这不是宾馆 -不是
- It's not a hotel.- No.
有粪便的味道
It smells of excrement!
哦哇 看这个
Oh, wow, look at this!
这里依然还有 像盘子
There's still, like, plates
杯子 茶碟和别的东西在这里
and cups and saucers and things in here.
我可以告诉你这是什么
I'll tell you exactly what this is.
这是一个废弃矿山
It's an abandoned mine.
他们在纳米比亚采矿不是吗
They do mine round in Namibia, don't they?
他们采什么矿
What do they mine for?
-钻石 -钻石？
- Diamonds.- Diamonds?
是的 但如果采到了 他们是不会走的
Yeah, but they wouldn't have left if there were any.
很明显他们离开了 而且不止一天两天了
They obviously left,and not yesterday.
看着 这里没有路不是吗
Look, there's no road here,is there?
-没有 -没
- No.- No.
除此之外
Apart from anything else,
我们在黑夜里可找不到路
we can't find our way around in the dark
因为我们没办法导航
cause we can't navigate.
-其实我可以 -怎么做
- Well, I can.- How?
-怎么做 -星星
- How?- Stars.
-不 你不能 -我可以
- No, you can't.- I can.
我承认我很多事都做不到
I can't do very many things, I admit...
任何事 但是这个我能做到
...anything,but I can do that.
你怎么用星星来导航
How do you navigate by the stars?
恩 找到南十字
Uh...find the Southern Cross.
可以 但是那可太复杂了
Yeah, but that's really complicated.
好吧 你想睡在粪坑里吗
Right, do you want to sleep in the excrement mine?
不 这个排除
No, this is out.
所以我们必须继续走
So, we have to keep going,
不管我们喜欢与否 直到我们找到
whether we like it or not,till we find...
我们必须 所以听着
We have to, so listen.
我应该能找到南十字星
I shall find the Southern Cross.
你不能用锤子来找南十字星
You can't find the Southern Cross with a hammer.
我找到了 哈哈我找到了 它在那里
I've found it!Ha! I've found it. It's there.
它就像个风筝
It's like a kite.
-那里的那个？ -对
- That one there?- Yeah.
它是风筝状的 有点像
It's a kite shape. It's sort of...
现在 你把长轴
Now, you take the long axis, yes?
-好的 -嗯
- Yes.- Mm-hm.
画一条假想线
And draw an imaginary line
穿过它 直到地平线
through it,down to the horizon.
好了吗 现在你把它相交
Yes? Now, you intersect it
于另外两颗星之间的连线
from a line drawn between two other stars,
这两条假想线的交点
and where those two imaginary lines meet,
正下方就是正南方
directly underneath it is due south.
所以如果这两个
So if it's those two--
也正是这两个 我能确定
which it is, I'm sure of it--
你画根线
you draw a line...
哦这真是个坏主意
Oh, this is a bad idea!
我们现在把命交给了一只
We are now trusting our lives to an orangutan
觉得自己是帕特里克 摩尔的大猩猩
who thinks he's Patrick Moore.
帕特里克·摩尔 BBC天文科普节目"仰望夜空"主持人
在那里  这里有两颗星
There it is. There's the two stars.
画根线
Draw a line...
你没给我什么指示啊 杰里米 方向对吗
I'm not getting many directions from you, Jeremy. Is this right?
你有点朝右过头了
You're heading a little bit too much to the right.
你得朝左一点
You need to go left a bit.
好 好 哦我真是太自信了
Good, good. Oh, I'm so confident.
等到太阳升起你们就会尝到屈辱的滋味的
You two are going to be eating humble pie when the sun comes up.
尽管杰里米·哥伦布
Despite the confidence
是如此自信满满
of Jeremy Columbus,
没有路出现
no road appeared.
哦这太糟糕了
Oh, this is grim.
抱歉
Excuse me.
我已经开了很长很长的时间了
I've been on the go a very, very long time now.
伙计们 对不住了 我不想再往前开一点点了
Guys, I'm sorry. I'm not driving another inch.
我做不到
I can't do this.
现在是凌晨三点
It's three o'clock in the morning.
我已经被榨干了
I'm exhausted.
他说的很有道理
He does have a point.
第二天早上
The next morning,
我们睡在沙子上醒来
we woke, having slept on the sand,
蜷缩在引擎边上为了取暖
huddled round our engines for warmth.
你个笨蛋 那是什么
You muppet. What's that?
嗯
Um...
嗯什么嗯
"Um" what?
我从不知道 纳米比亚有两个海
I never knew Namibia had two seas.
它才没有两个海
It doesn't have two seas.
没有 它有一个巨大的C(Cleckson)在这里
No, it has one massive "cee" in it.
一个巨大的 愚蠢的C
One massive, stupid "cee"
将我们带回到了我们出发的地方
that's navigated us back to where we started.
-我可以说 -这不是我 我
- Can I just say...- It wasn't my... I...
为什么我们会相信你能用星星来导航
Why did we even believe you could navigate by the stars?
你甚至都不能读指南针
You can't even read a compass.
有两个C  这里有C
There are two "cees". There's two "cees" here
竟然会相信那个C可以为我们指明方向
for believing that that "cee" could navigate us.
-是的 你没错 -我也许不能
- No, you're right.- I couldn't possibly...
真的 我无法理解
Really, I don't understand that.
超级冷 脸上像被砂纸刮
Freezing cold, sandpapered on the face...
-你穿着件大衣呢 -它很薄 你感受过没有
- You've got a coat on.- It's thin. Have you felt it?
我连一件薄外套都没有
I haven't even got a thin coat.
我只有一件T恤 不管怎样
I've only got a T-shirt. Anyway,
我才不要和你争
I'm not going to be competitive with you
谁最冷
about who's the coldest.
我才是最冷的 -我们都是最迷失的
- I'm the coldest!- We're all the lostest
没关系 听着 我们不要再被困下去了
Never mind. Look, let's not get bogged down
不管究竟是谁的错
with whose fault it was.
要不是你我们才不会被困在这里
There's no being bogged down with it, is there?
都是你的错
It was yours.
我们可以重新回到沙漠里
We can either go back into the desert
寻找一条路
to look for a road,
或者我们可以继续昨天做过的事
or we can just do what we were doing yesterday,
待在沙漠里
and stay on the beach.
至少我们知道 如果我们让海在我们的左边
At least we know, if we keep the sea on our left,
我们就可以往北方走
we're going north.
-是的 -这很有道理
- Yes. - That's a fair point.
-让我们用海来导航 -是的
- Let's navigate by the sea. - Yes.
在我们的新  好吧 稍新的
With our new-- well, newish--
预备计划下
plan in place,
我们再一次出发
we set off once more.
现在我们在的地方 这些是我们昨天留下的胎痕
So here we are. These are our wheel marks from yesterday.
24小时的寒冷 悲惨
24 hours of cold, misery...
却毫无所获
to achieve exactly nothing.
我是说 真的什么都没有
I mean, it is exactly nothing.
但是 除了这个还有这天气
But, apart from that and the weather...
还有大猩猩 别的都进展顺利
and Jeremy Clarkson, it's all going really well.
我们一路向北
As we continued north,
前日的悲惨在我们周围的壮丽景色下
the misery of the previous day was banished
都犹如过眼云烟
by the sheer bigness of our surroundings.
哦这真是个令人惊叹的地方
Oh, this is an astonishing place.
有个好似珠穆拉玛峰般高耸的沙丘在我的右边
I've got a dune the size of Mount Everest to my right,
大西洋在我的左边
the Atlantic Ocean to my left...
这简直如史诗一般
This is absolutely epic.
这才是沙滩车之旅
This is proper beach buggy driving.
太阳缓缓落下 大海就在那里被浪花拍打
Sun's out, sea's there with the surf.
这就像海滩男孩一样（乐队名称）
It's like being in the Beach Boys.
尽管这一切都很迷人 但是
Amidst all this loveliness, though,
但是房间里还是有个大问题
there was one small elephant edging its way into the room.
伙计们 我实在不想说这个
Chaps, I don't want to have to say this,
但现在是涨潮还是退潮
but is the tide coming in or going out?
恩 我猜是涨潮
Uh...I'm guessing in.
不可能会涨到那里
There's no way up the sides of that.
但是如果潮水真的进来了这么多 看上去是这样的
And if the tide comes in that far, which it does,
我们就没辙了
we've had it.
在这里必须一直开
Got to keep moving here.
我们可承受不起被困在这里
We cannot afford to get stuck.
随着几次慷慨的大脚踩油门
With some generous use of the throttle,
我们设法逃出了
we managed to get clear
海和沙丘的钳制
of the sea-and-sand-dune pincer movement.
但是接着我们又遇到了另一个问题
But then we had another problem.
这就是沙滩的尽头
I'd say that was the end of the beach.
它怎么会这样直接到头?
How does that just end like that?
它就是这么到头了 -这里就是尽头
It does just end. That is the end.
而且纳米比亚政府不允许我们
And the Namibian government doesn't allow us
在盐碱滩上开 而这里就是
to drive on the salt pans, and that's what that is.
这就意味着 根据詹姆斯的话
This meant, according to James,
我们只剩一条路可以走
we had only one option.
那就是回到我们的起点
We've got to go back the way we came.
但是假如潮水涨进来
But if the tide's coming in,
那狭窄的通道将会变得无法通过
that narrow bit will have become impassable.
因此我想到 如果看到一个好的机会左转
That's why I think if we see a good opportunity to turn left,
比如像我们昨天晚上 我们就左转
like we did last night, we do it.
你真是建议我们回到……
Are you honestly suggesting we go back in the...
是的 我们还能去哪儿呢
Well, where else can we go?
我们要么被淹死 要么就是饿死
We'll either drown or starve otherwise.
好的 我们只要找到一个小通道
Right, we've just got to find a bit
让我们在涨潮之前进入内陆
where we can get inland before the tide comes in.
潮水快要涨到那里了
That is getting closer to that,
如果那个发生了 我们就完了
and when that happens, we've had it.
在我们势如破竹的前进时
But as we thundered along,
沙丘拒绝打开通道让我们驶入
the dunes refused to open up and let us in.
海来了啊
That's the sea!
海在这里了
It's the sea, there!
哦它在冲我而来
Oh, it's coming at me!
我还是坚持我们没有办法逃离这里 看着
I still say we can't get out here, look.
现在没有办法左转
No left turn at the moment.
正是需要V8的时候
This is where you need a V8!
卧槽
Oh, shit.
哦杰里米有麻烦了
Oh, Jeremy's in trouble!
那看上去可不好
That is not looking good!
来啊 来啊
Come on, come on. Whoa.
哦不
Oh, no.
哦不 别在这出问题啊
Oh, no. No, no, no. Not a good place.
哦天哪
- Oh, God.
嗯  我在海里了
Uh...I'm in the sea.
因为这算是一个紧急情况
Because it was a bit of an emergency,
我的同事决定来帮我一次
my colleagues decided to help for once.
走起
- Go.
不
No.
它就这么在空转吗
Is that just spinning?
它在那里被搁浅了
It's beached under there.
我直接开车推他就可以了
I don't see why I can't push him with that.
-好吧 那就试试 -好的
-All right, then. Try. -All right.
詹姆斯 算上我们
James, count us in.
三 二 一 走
Three, two, one, away!
-耶  -好 出发吧
Yes!  Right, let's go!
我的搁浅消耗了本来就紧张的时间
Me getting beached cost us time we never had in the first place,
而且我们还深陷其中
and we were still trapped.
老天爷
Jesus Christ.
水位越来越高了
Ah, it's coming in.
冲啊
Come on, come on, come on.
快走啊
Come on.
这可不妙
Oh, that's bad.
操
Shit.
宝贝加把劲
Come on, baby, come on.
幸好 沙丘终于到了尽头
Mercifully, the dunes finally started to fall away
我们总算逃过一劫
and we were saved.
-我们可算过来了  -没错
-And we're through! -We are, we are.
终于能松口气了
That's a relief.
刚才差点出不来
So nearly got stuck then.
我们已上路36个小时
We'd now been on the go for 36 hours,
却再次回到了起点
and we were pretty much back where we started from... again.
全身湿透的我们又冷又累
We were also soaked, frozen, worn out,
由于没有食物
and because we had no food with us,
也是饥肠辘辘
we were also hungry.
但贝爷克拉克森想来荒野求生了
But then Bear Clarkson came to the rescue.
你能去找点浮木生火吗
Cold you go and get some driftwood for a fire?
你来搭个简易烧烤架之类的吧
And could you fashion a rudimentary barbecue grill of some sort?
好吧 你从哪找的鱼竿
OK. Where did you get the fishing rod from?
这是我沙滩车上的天线
It's my whip aerial. It's a beach buggy.
-我早有准备  -这就是鱼竿
- I thought of that. - They're fishing rods.
看 这是个完美的烤鱼架
This is going to make a perfect little fish grill thing, look.
你生好火了吗
Have you got a fire lit yet?
你不是负责钓鱼吗
I thought you were fishing.
是啊 我的车在钓
I am fishing. My car's fishing.
-看  -是吗
- Look. - Well, is it?
-我把鱼竿固定好了 -就停那了啊
- Yeah, look, I've got the rods attached. - It's parked.
-那是什么  -烧烤架
What's that? That's the grill.
用我工具箱里的钳子固定好架子
So we hold that with the pliers from my multi-tool,
把鱼切成片
cut the fish up, fillet it...
你行吗 当我没问 他也就能开个罐头
Can you do that? There's no point asking him. He can open a tin...
你会片鱼吗
Can you fillet a fish?
-只有鱼吗  -这是在海边啊
- What, is it only fish? - Well, it's the sea!
你还想抓什么 鸡?
What did you think I was going to catch, a chicken?
我的天
Oh, my God!
-不是吧  -等等
Oh, my God! No, wait. Yes!
在哈蒙德去找浮木时
While Hammond went off to get more driftwood,
我和詹姆斯准备剖鱼
James and I set about gutting the catch.
把他的车当砧板 好样的
Use his car as the table. There we go.
-那就是它的内脏 你找到了  -没错
- That's his gut. Look. You've got it. - Yeah, right.
完蛋
Oh, God. Shit. Look,
看 真的全掉在排气管上了
it's all gone literally onto his exhaust.
真糟糕 算了 这需要你帮忙
Oh, no. Never mind. Look, I need your help.
把头切下来
Right, saw its head off.
-可以了  -真棒
- Ah, there we go. - Excellent.
-我觉得 但又不确定  -掉他座位下去了
- I think, but I'm not sure-- - It's gone under his seat.
真的吗 不会吧
Oh, no. Has it?
没事 待会再打扫
It's all right, I'll get it out later.
这也算是美味了
Oh, it's done a treat, this.
哈蒙德 看这
Look at this, Hammond.
味道挺不错
Oh, that's all right, isn't it?
这就是鱼的味道
It tastes like fish, doesn't it?
谁想来瓶啤酒吗
OK, does anybody want a beer?
-你带了吗  -没有
- Have you got some? - No.
去死吧
- Oh, you...
真想捅死你
- That deserves a stabbing.
可不是吗
That is a proper stabbing.
太过分了
That's properly out of order.
午餐后
After lunch,
我们再次向沙丘深处进军
we set off once more into the dunes.
这次我们向东前行
Right, so let's keep heading east.
我们必须得找到路了
And we must come to a road at some...
总会有条路吧
There has to be a road.
但 一路走来
But, for mile after mile,
还真没有
there wasn't.
这是纳米布沙漠
It's the Namib Desert.
纳米布在当地方言中意味着 虚无的广阔
"Namib" in the local dialect means "big nothing".
这定是世界上最美的沙漠
It must be the prettiest desert in the world.
一望无际的沙丘
It's just a sea of dunes.
沙丘开始越来越陡
Dunes which were getting bigger.
老天爷 这沙丘是有多大
Bloody Nora, look at the size of that!
释放这180匹马力
Engaging 180 horsepower.
用两驱的沙滩车爬沙丘
Climbing them in our two-wheel-drive beach buggies
变得愈加困难
was becoming tricky.
加把力 你可以的 没问题的
Come on, you can do this. You can do this!
但凭借V8引擎 我终究还是爬上了
But by deploying the V8, I was sort of all right.
好样的
Yes!
哈蒙德因为轮胎抓地力够强 也成功爬上
Hammond had grippy tyres, so he was all right, too.
一定要爬上去啊
Please, make it. Please.
拜托
Please!
就是这样
There you go!
然而 对于上世纪60年代的车
However, back in the 1960s...
别给我丢人啊 小车
Come on, little car.
别这样
- Oh, no, no, no.
不要啊
No, no.
-陷地了吗  -对
- Stuck? - Yes.
两个问题 第一
Two problems. Number one,
他装了台90匹马力引擎
he's put a 90 horsepower engine in it,
可能实际只剩40匹了
which actually is probably only 40.
-可不是吗  -第二
- Yeah. - And number two,
他从来不踩地板油
he will not use full power ever.
他有90匹引擎 和5匹的脚
Well, he's got a 90 horsepower engine, but a 5 horsepower foot.
我敢打赌 他肯定会说 车缺缸了
And I bet you any money he's saying "I had a misfire."
你得把油门踩到底
You've got to push the accelerator all the way to--
我知道 可是
I know, but... I know that.
它有时候会缺缸
It occasionally has a little misfire moment,
我就滑下去了
and then I lose it.
我就知道
- He said it!
下午继续征程
And so the afternoon continued.
咕噜号和勇敢号继续前行
The Grunt Machine and the Grit Machine would forge ahead...
打死我我也不干
There is no way in hell I'm doing this!
太给力了
You star!
当然
...and then there'd be
还有那不可避免的通讯交流
the inevitable radio exchange.
杰里米 我们怎么少了个人
We appear to be a man down, Jeremy.
詹姆斯梅 你在哪
James May, where are you?
因为我们浪费太多时间
Because we spent so much time
等待缺缸船长
waiting for Captain Misfire,
日落时 我们还未走出沙漠
we were still in the desert as dusk fell.
逐渐减弱的光线也意味着难以识辨路障
And failing light meant it was hard to spot obstacles.
状况报告
Right, sit rep.
卧  槽
Jesus (BLEEP) Christ!
我的天
-Holy...
天啊
-Oh, my God!
完蛋
Oh, shit!
看啊
Look at it!
伙计 我得去瞧瞧
Mate, I've got to have a look.
这是要我的命
Oh, shitty death...
-我的刹车都抱死了 太吓人了  -看 车都给埋了
- I locked up. That was just... - Look, he's buried!
-车头完全埋进沙子里了  -我完全踩死了
- You've buried the front. - I was completely locked up.
差点就开下去
'Cause I would have gone down that.
好险
- (RICHARD LAUGHS) - Look at it!
这次的有惊无险是在提醒我们
My close shave was a reminder that, after dark,
天色变暗 沙丘中暗藏杀机
these dunes would become very, very dangerous.
越来越难分辨地形了
It's getting harder and harder to read the terrain now.
那是下坡还是上坡
Is that a drop? Is that a hill?
是往上走 还是悬崖 看不清
Is that going up? Is that a cliff? What is it?
危险
Peril... peril.
哦 操
Oh, shit!
哦我觉得那里有个坑
Oh, I think there's a drop off there.
这就是一个漆黑的深渊
It's just a black abyss.
那可能又是一个大悬崖
That could be a huge cliff again.
终于 我们再也受不了
Eventually, we could take no more,
第二个晚上 我们又在引擎边定居了
and we had to settle down for a second night around our engines.
沙漠第3日
我们会找到路的 那里肯定有
We will find a road. There must...
-它不会 它不会就这样没完没了的不是吗 -不会的
It can't... It can't║go on forever, can it?║- No.
它肯定 会有一个镇 一条路 或者什么
It has to... There will be a town, a road... something.
不幸的是 为了寻找救援
Unfortunately, to find salvation,
我们还需要越过更多的山丘
we still had to climb more dunes.
爬上去然后又从另外一边爬下来
Climb them and then get down the other side.
哦我的天哪
Oh, my God!
这就是悬崖啊
Well, that's just a cliff!
呜 啊啊
Whoa! Aargh!
哇 这就是个怪兽
Whoa, this is a monster.
哦 我做不到啊
Oh! (BLEEP) I don't think I can do...!
哇哦哦哦
Whoa-ho-ho-ho!
哇啊啊啊啊
Whoa-a-a-a-a-a!
让我们开始吧
Here we go.
我们三个人 不约而同地
All three of us simultaneously...
天哪
Holy shit.
我没有怕
I wasn't scared.
哦我的上帝啊
Oh, my God.
伙计们 这是迄今为止最大的一个
Guys, this is the biggest yet by a country mile.
是再说那条坡道的尺寸
Is that the size of the drop
还是他那块儿发生了点什么
or what's happened to his penis?
好了 看看他们都在大惊小什么
Right, then. Let's see what all the fuss is about.
我的天啊
Holy shit!
哦哦哦
Oh-h-h-h-h!
现在把轮胎打直 理查德
And now straighten those wheels, Richard,
掰直它们
straighten them,
因为你要直直的下落
because you've got to go down straight.
天哪
Holy shit. Oh-h-h-h-h, shit!
这太吓人了
That is frightening.
爱死这片沙漠了
Love this desert.
我从来也没有比在这片沙漠里
I'm never, ever, ever happier
更开心过
than I am when I'm in a desert.
这里 这里是我去过的最好的沙漠
And this... this is the best desert I've ever been to.
你永远也不愁没有景色可观赏
You can never really lose sight of the fact, though,
它实际上是一个
that what it actually is
巨大的橙色杀人机器
is a big, orange killing engine.
一个巨大的山坡要来了 没有什么办法
Now, a big crest's coming up. No idea.
不知道下面是 缓和的丘陵 还是巨大的悬崖
Gentle rolling hill or massive cliff?
我不知道 哈蒙德
I don't know, Hammond!
哈蒙德 你是认真的吗
Hammond, seriously.
哦 他去了
Shit, he's gone.
哈蒙德去了各位 哈蒙德去了 玩大了
Hammond's gone, everyone. Hammond's gone. Big one.
哦 卧槽
Oh, (BLEEP) me.
你特么是怎么下去的
How the (BLEEP) did you get down that?
眼睛一闭就下来了
With my eyes shut!
太可怕了
That was terrifying!
天啊
Jesus!
当我们继续朝东进发
As we continued to head east,
地势终于平坦了一点
the terrain eventually levelled out...
这意味着我们从惊恐  变成了极度不舒服
which meant we swapped terror for extreme discomfort.
哦我的老天啊
Ah. Oh, God Almighty.
我不认为这些车是被设计成
I don't think these cars were actually designed
来经受这些惩罚
to take this much punishment.
我还知道我们也不是呢
- And I know we weren't.
唯一的是
The only thing is,
詹姆斯的车比这个低 那还会更糟
James's car rides lower than this and will be worse.
啊噢
Argh! Ow!
很快 这无休止的连续猛击
Soon, the relentless battering
开始造成故障
started to cause breakdowns.
沙子 沙子进到变速杆了
Sand... Sand in gear shift.
我的油门被卡住了 同志们
My throttle is jammed wide open, people.
问题是这里的空滤
The problem is that every time the air filter, here,
会随着我的驾驶转动
turns as I'm driving along-- which it does--
就会把油门拉线卡住
it's jamming the throttle.
出什么事了
What's going on here?
怎么了
What's up?
油门被卡住了
The throttle is now jamming
一直是全开的状态
fully open all the time.
哦 麻烦了
Oh, problem.
上帝啊
Oh, God.
它还会移动
It is still moving.
在队伍的前方
Many miles ahead,
因为这永无止境的颠簸 我们不得不停车
we'd pulled over for a break from the endless bumps,
而詹姆斯变得很有趣
and James was being very interesting!
这个帽子好的地方在于 你可以像定日镜一样调整它的角度
The good thing about this hat is you can angle it, like a heliostat,
到太阳照射的地方
to where the sun's coming from.
是的 没错
Yes, that's true.
但你的头还是像乳头
But you still look a tit.
哈蒙德真幸运 能有个伙伴
Luckily for Hammond, who could do with the company,
我继续移动
I was back on the move.
好 现在需要一种新的驾驶风格
Right, a new style of driving is now required.
这个手臂用来转向 这个手臂用来换档
This arm for steering, this arm for changing gear,
然后另一只手臂用来减速 像这样
and then another arm for deaccelerating, like so.
耶
Yes!
加速
Accelerate.
减速
Deaccelerate.
有时候 当你仔细聆听
Sometimes, if you listen very carefully,
甚至可以听到我的天才
you can hear my genius.
回到三人组 我们继续
Back as a threesome, we continued
这看似没完没了向东的旅行
with our seemingly endless journey to the east.
只需要找到一条路 这可不再有趣了
Just need to find a road now. This is not funny any more.
受够了沙漠
Enough desert.
我可不想在沙漠里再过一夜
I don't want another night in the desert.
我闻起来太糟糕了
I smell pretty bad.
我怀疑如果我们能够
And I suspect that if we manage
在今晚找到一些有人烟的地方
to find somewhere tonight near civilisation,
我们很可能会办一个庆典
we should probably have a ceremonial
用内裤点起篝火
bonfire of the underpants.
说真的 虽然
In truth, though,
我觉得我们会永远困在沙漠里
I thought we'd be in the desert forever.
但是 在下午的晚些时候
But then, late in the afternoon...
我向前眺望 没再看到一望无际的沙海
I'm looking ahead, and I'm not seeing an endless sea of sand.
我看到绿色
I'm seeing green.
树！ 那是树和灌木丛
Trees! Those are trees and shrubs!
电线杆
Pylons!
电线杆！ 那意味着有电
Pylons! That means electricity.
哦耶
Oh, yes!
找到文明了
Civilisation!
最棒的是
And then, best of all...
哦我的天啊
Oh, my God.
我真以为又要再睡在
I honestly thought we had another night of sleeping...
沙子里
-- ...in the sand.
但是 不 看这些
But, no! Look at it!
这景象实在太美好了
Nicest thing I've ever seen.
我可以朝东 我可以朝西
I could go east, I could go west...
不管你走哪条路 总会到达某些地方 这才是重点
Whichever way you go, it goes somewhere. That's the point.
这是一条路 它通向某处
It's a road, it goes somewhere.
你知道我们刚刚做了什么吧
You know what we've just done, don't you?
我们用三辆沙滩车穿越了纳米布沙漠
We've just crossed the Namib Desert in three beach buggies.
-我们做到了 -我们成功了
- We have. - We did.
我们做到了
We did.
没有什么可以阻挡我们了
There is literally nothing can stop us now.
无可否认
Admittedly,
我们的穿越并没有完全走直线
our crossing had not exactly been as the crow flies,
但是我们找到了我们的路
but we had found our road,
这才是最重要的
and that's all that mattered.
哦耶
Oh, yes!
这是我见到最好的事了
That's the best thing I've ever seen!
那是什么鬼?
- What the hell was that?
我的车后面好像有东西炸了
Something has just exploded at the back of my car.
我的天
Oh, dear.
当我的同事们回来找到我的时候
By the time my colleague shad got back to me,
我找出了问题所在
I'd worked out what the problem was.
其实问题很简单
It's really straight forward, OK?
-减震器最上面的螺丝伸出来了 -对
- The top bolt has come out of the shock absorber.- Right.
螺丝爆出来 射穿了冷却管
It shot up, boinged into the coolant pipe,
约14升的水就直接炸了出去
and three gallons of water have simply burst out,
溅的到处都是 唯独没进到引擎里
going everywhere except into the engine.
-对 -所以我只需要把那个螺栓装回去
- Right.- So all I've got to dois reattach the top bolt...
修好水管 然后找到14升的水
mend the pipe and find three gallons of water...
水应该可以找一个过路的司机要到 然后就能上路了
which I shall get from a passing motorist,and I'll be on my way.
好的
Right.
我只需要你们可以帮我
All I could do with a hand with
把这车子抬起来
is just lifting the car up
所以我可以重新装 呃
so I can reattach the, um...
对 不过这里会有人吗?
Yeah. Well,is there anybody here?
-这里 -我觉得迟早会有人经过这里的
- There's...- I suppose a motorist will pass eventually.
他可以给你水 帮你把车子抬起来
The one that gives you water will also lift it up for you.
你们只需要帮我抬起来一点点
You could just lift it up a little bit.
或者我们可以去喝点啤酒
Or we could goand have a beer.
有车来啦
I hear traffic.
我们可不想打扰你们
We don't want to interfere when you're trying to talk
人家可能会被我们吓跑
'cause we might put them off.
好吧
Right.
这里直走应该会有个地方
Somewhere along here there will be a place,
有个酒吧之类的
and that place will have a bar in it
就会有啤酒喝
that will contain beer.
你有水吗
Do you have any water?
-哈? -水
- Huh?- Water.
因为我的散热器炸了
Because the radiator has blown,
所以我需要大概14升
so I need just three gallons.
看 你这里有水的 我只要一桶
Look, you've got some water there. Just a bucket.
这就是辆运水车
It's an actual water lorry...
而且还在漏水 但是他就不肯给我点
leaking water,and he won't give me any.
终于 我找到了一个本地人
Eventually,I flagged down a local
愿意分给我一些水
who had water to spare.
谢谢
Thank you.
然后我开始了维修
And then I got on with the repairs.
这是一个重新安装的避震器
That is one reassembled shock absorber.
把这个重新装上
That's reattached,
这样冷却系统就复原了
so that's the cooling system back in one piece.
经过五小时无聊的旅程
After an exhausting five-hour drive,
理查德和我终于找到了一个小镇
Richard and I finally reached a town,
其实是纳米比亚的首都温得和克
which turned out to be Namibia's capital city:Windhoek,
我们终于也找到了水
and we too were taking on liquids.
唔
Mm.
至于还在路上的某人
Back out on the highway, though,
情况就不那么乐观了
things weren't so good.
我现在正在开的 或者试图驾驶的 是阿波罗13号
What I'm driving here -or attempting to drive -is Apollo 13.
阿波罗13号 以宇航空难为题材的纪录片
比喻自己开这车正冒着极大风险
冷却系统里进了空气
There's some air trapped in the system
所以我得在前面开一个小口
and I've had to makea small hole in the front
这样才能够到散热器
to get at the radiator.
把那个抽出来
Bled that,
进到引擎里的都会抽出来
bled all the stuff going into the engine.
这是总管
This is the header pipe.
所有东西都没了 然后
Everything is bled, and yet,
开一英里 就过热
you do a mile, it overheats.
再开一英里 又过热
Another mile, overheats.
我们4小时开了 32公里
Well, we've covered...20 miles in four hours.
这是48公里中的第六次了
This is the sixth time in 30 miles that's happened.
当我的同事们享受啤酒和睡床的时候
Whilst my colleagues embraced beer and bed,
我还坚持在我一生中最艰难 最寒冷
I steeled myself for the longest, coldest,
最无助的夜晚
most frustrating night of my life.
下集预告...
路况变差了
The roads are getting worse.
说实话 我感觉我的骨头都要散架了
Honestly, my bones are going to shatter.
我的天
- Oh, my God!
-我有个好主意 -哦不
- I've had a great idea.- Oh, no.
我的天 这个太高啦
Oh, shit, it's really high!